
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> ABC19980120.1830.0957 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="broadcast news"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<BODY>

<section endTime="1094.00" startTime="957.31" type="report">
<TEXT>

 For his part, Fidel Castro is the ultimate political survivor. People have predicted his demise so many times, and the US has tried to hasten it on
 several occasions. Time and again, he endures. He has outlasted and
 sometimes outsmarted eight American presidents.
 Fidel Castro invited John Paul to come for a reason. This is clearly an
 opportunity for Cuba to look good internationally.


 The entire world will see images of the Pope in Cuba. They'll see images
 of
 the Pope with Fidel Castro. It will give the rest of the world the view
 that Cuba is like any other nation, something the US has, of course,
 tried to persuade the world that it is not .


 For nearly forty years, the United States has said categorically it would not tolerate totalitarian rule in its own backyard. It is the US economic
 and political embargo which has kept Cuba in a box.


 The main positive for Castro to invite the Pope is international, to be
 able
 to say to the rest of the world, this government is not  as closed, as
 intolerant, uh as totalitarian as some make it out to be.


 One of the scenarios widely advanced before the visit is that through the
 Pope, Cuba, still led by Castro, can begin a more productive relationship
 with the world. That will, in turn, bring pressure on Washington to change.


 Those observers looking for a battle between uncompromising representatives
 and very different ideologies will, in all likelihood, be disappointed.


 Castro has said that you can be a Communist and still be a
 Christian. He says he and the Pope both want to end the exploitation of
 man by man. The question is who will Cubans believe?


 The main negative is the risk that the Pope's visit will persuade a great
 many more Cubans to break loose of the Cuban government. If so, then the
 Pope's visit would really open up a new chapter in the government's
 relations with its own society. For the Cuban government, that is the
 risk.


 At the end of the broadcast this evening, one more trip around Havana to see
 what it's been like since the last time. And in just a moment Diane Sawyer will have some other news.

</TEXT>
</section>

</BODY>

































































































































</TimeML>
