
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980306.1001 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/06/1998 13:19:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2188 Cx1f wstm-
u i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Iraq 3rdLd-Writethru   03-06 0642
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru 
<HEADLINE>
American Ritter resumes inspections in Iraq
</HEADLINE>
UR Eds: AMs; RECASTS throughout with Ritter inspecting three sensitive
sites; UN quotes QL
UR By LEON BARKHO QC
UR Associated Press Writer QC

<TEXT>
BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) _ An American leader of a U.N. weapons
inspection team resumed work in Iraq Friday, nearly two months
after his team was effectively blocked.
Scott Ritter led his team on a 10-hour tour of three suspected
weapons sites classified as ``sensitive'' by the Iraqi authorities,
U.N. spokesman Alan Dacey said.
``All sites were inspected to the satisfaction of the inspection
team and with full cooperation of Iraqi authorities,'' Dacey said.
At least one of the sensitive sites was a barracks of the elite
Republican Guard, a well-placed source told The Associated Press.
Previously the Iraqis have resisted attempts to inspect such
quarters.
The U.N. Security Council has charged the inspectors with
verifying that Iraq has destroyed its long-range missiles and
weapons of mass destruction.
It was <COMMENT NOTE="Not sure how to  capture this">the first time</COMMENT> that Ritter, who arrived Thursday with
some 50 inspectors for a tour likely to last over a week, had been allowed to carry out an inspection since Jan. 13.
Then the Baghdad government stopped providing Ritter's team with
escorts, making it impossible for him to enter any site. Iraq
alleged Ritter was an American spy whose team had a
disproportionately high number of Americans and Britons.
The official Iraqi News Agency, which gives the daily tally of
inspections, did not mention Ritter by name, but said Friday that
team no. 225 _ which Ritter heads _ made surprise visits to a
number of sites and was assisted by aerial surveillance.
Five other U.N. inspection teams visited a total of nine other
sites, the agency reported.
An Iraqi official, speaking on customary condition of anonymity,
said Ritter would not try to visit any of the eight presidential
sites that Baghdad had placed off-limits to U.N. weapons
inspectors.
The official said these sites could only be visited by a special
team of U.N. monitors and diplomats as laid down by the Feb. 23
accord signed by U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan and Iraqi Deputy
Prime Minister Tariq Aziz.
Ritter's return is seen as something of a test of that
agreement, under which Iraq agreed to give inspectors full access
to eight of Saddam Hussein's presidential palaces.
The United States had moved additional troops and a naval armada
into the Gulf and said it would strike Iraq <COMMENT NOTE="I don't think we can capture this kind of construction">unless it gave </COMMENT>the U.N.
arms inspectors unfettered access to all potential weapons sites,
including Saddam's palaces. Iraq had argued the presidential sites
should be off limits as symbols of sovereignty.
A Pentagon spokesman said Thursday that the 38,000 U.S. troops
in the Gulf will remain until Iraq complies with the U.N. Security
Council agreement over weapons inspections.
``We are going to maintain our forces in the region for the
foreseeable future,'' said spokesman Kenneth Bacon.
The U.N.-Iraq accord was worked out by U.N. Secretary-General
Kofi Annan, who appointed a retired Indian diplomat on Thursday as
his special representative to Iraq. Prakash Shah, 58, a former
Indian ambassador to the United Nations, is part of an effort by
Annan to expand contacts with the Iraqi leadership.
Palace inspections are not expected to start until the new
agreement's procedures are in place. U.N. officials in New York on
Friday finished drafting the rules, in consultation with Iraqi
diplomats. The procedures are due to go before the Security Council
next week.
The Security Council has said it will not lift the sweeping
sanctions imposed on Iraq after its 1990 invasion of Kuwait until
the U.N. inspectors certify that Baghdad has eliminated its weapons
of mass destruction.
</TEXT>
UR lb-jbm
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-06-98 1319EST
</TRAILER>







































































































































































</TimeML>
