
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980301.0720 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/01/1998 14:11:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1219 Cx1f wstm-
u i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Israel-Lebanon     03-01 0570
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Israel-Lebanon 
<HEADLINE>
Political momentum gathers for Israeli pullout from Lebanon
</HEADLINE>
UR Eds: INCORPORATES Israel-Syria; ADDS background and additional
comment Sunday QL

<TEXT>
JERUSALEM (AP) _ Top Israeli officials sent strong new signals
Sunday that Israel wants to withdraw from southern Lebanon, where a
costly war of attrition has been steadily claiming soldiers' lives.
Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu told his Cabinet on Sunday
that Israel was willing to withdraw from southern Lebanon provided
Israel's northern frontier could be secured.
``If the Lebanese government will cooperate with us in making
appropriate security arrangements in south Lebanon, we will be
happy to get out of Lebanon in the framework of implementation of
U.N. Resolution 425,'' Netanyahu told his ministers.
That 1978 resolution calls for Israel's unconditional withdrawal
from the self-declared security zone it occupies in south Lebanon,
and for the deployment of the Lebanese army and U.N. forces to ensure security along the Lebanese-Israeli border.
On Friday, Netanyahu said he had ``no qualms'' about
implementing the U.N. resolution, as long as Israel had ``the
necessary security safeguards.''
Cabinet minister Michael Eitan said Sunday that Netanyahu's
remarks marked a substantive change in Israel's position.
``We will defend our north from the international border,'' said
Eitan, the science minister. ``No one wants to stay in Lebanon;
thus we think it better to withdraw.''
Uri Lubrani, Israel's top official for Lebanon affairs, also suggested Israel was willing to modify its political goals in
Lebanon.
``This is a new thing...it means that we are willing to talk
today _ full stop _ about security,'' Lubrani told Israel's Channel
One. ``We have gotten off the issue of peace, off the issue of
normalization.''
As the death toll in Lebanon has mounted, the Israeli government
has been faced with a growing grassroots movement calling for
Israel's unilateral withdrawal from Lebanon.
Since 1985 _ when the Israelis created a security buffer zone
southern Lebanon _ nearly 200 Israeli soldiers have been killed
fighting Hezbollah and other guerrillas. Last week, Hezbollah
fighters killed three Israeli soldiers and seriously wounded six
others.
The Israelis suffered a record 39 deaths in southern Lebanon
last year. In addition, 73 soldiers were killed en route to Lebanon
when two military helicopters crashed last February.
The Maariv newspaper said Sunday that Netanyahu's comments last
week were in response to signals from Syria that it wants to renew
the long-stalled peace talks between the two countries.
The newspaper, quoting ``secret reports,'' said Syria had indicated its interest in resuming talks in remarks made last week
by the Syrian ambassador to Washington, Walid Mualem, in a lecture
to a closed forum in Baltimore.
Two top aides to Netanyahu, political adviser Uzi Arad and
Cabinet Secretary Danny Naveh, left for Europe on Sunday,
apparently to investigate the Syrian issue, the newspaper said.
Israel-Syrian talks have been cut off for nearly two years.
Defense Minister Yitzhak Mordechai was the first senior Israeli
official to refer to U.N. resolution 425 in a speech six weeks ago,
saying at the time he was willing to withdraw troops in exchange
for guarantees that Israel would not be attacked.
</TEXT>
UR (pvs-dh-lk)
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Israel-Lebanon; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-01-98 1411EST
</TRAILER>































































































































































































</TimeML>
