
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980213.1380 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 15:44:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2227 Cx1f wstm-
r i Cx13  Cx11  BC-PuertoRico-HostageKil     02-13 0243
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Puerto Rico-Hostage Killed,0246 
<HEADLINE>
Police discover dismembered body of man kidnapped Wednesday
</HEADLINE>
UR By HILARIO DE LEON QC
UR Associated Press Writer QC

<TEXT>
CAGUAS, Puerto Rico (AP) _ Kidnappers kept their promise to kill
a store owner they took hostage and police found the man's
dismembered and decapitated body Friday wrapped in plastic garbage
bags.
Police confirmed Friday that the body found along a highway in
this municipality 15 miles south of San Juan belonged to Jorge
Hernandez, 49.
Hernandez  was kidnapped from his small, neighborhood store in
the town of Trujillo Alto at 10 p.m. Wednesday, police said. His
kidnappers demanded a ransom of dlrs 1 million, but negotiations
broke off at noon Thursday.
Police gave no details about the negotiations with the
kidnappers for the return of Hernandez.
The store owner's body  was found with the arms and head cut off
and the parts stuffed in separate garbage bags. A passerby called
police  to report the body alongside the road.
Puerto Rico Police Superintendent Pedro Toledo urged people who
might  be targeted by kidnappers to be alert.
``There has been an increase in Puerto Rico in this kind of
thing and some of these bands of kidnappers  are made up of
foreigners,'' Toledo said.
While some Latin American countries such as Mexico and Colombia
 have suffered from a rash of kidnappings in recent years, the crime
has not been common in this U.S. commonwealth.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Puerto Rico-Hostage Killed; CT:i;
(REG:CRB;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1544EST
</TRAILER>





































































































</TimeML>
