
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> CNN19980213.2130.0155 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="broadcast news"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<BODY>

<section endTime="274.42" startTime="155.00" type="report">
<TEXT>

 President Clinton says he is committed to a possible strike against Iraq,
 despite objections from other countries.
 Steve Hurst has that.


 The US military buildup in the Persian gulf continues apace, more
 planes headed from the united states and senior officials say Iraq's
 president Saddam Hussein can expect punishing air strikes to continue well
 into the future if he does n't stop building biological and chemical
 weapons.


 Saddam will know by our actions and our warning that we will be prepared to act again if we have evidence he is trying to rebuild his weapons of mass
 destruction capabilities.


 In a bit of television diplomacy, Iraq's deputy foreign minister responded
 from Baghdad in less than one hour, saying Washington would break
 international law by attacking without UN approval.


 The united states is not authorized to use force before going to the
 council.


 President Clinton, meantime, glossed over stern warnings from Moscow on
 Thursday that US air strikes against Iraq could do serious harm to
 relations with the Kremlin.


 We're trying to find a diplomatic solution.
 And I hope that, whatever happens today, that our relationships with Russia
 will continue to be productive and constructive and strong, because that's
 very important to the future of our peoples.


 One contrary view of the issue presented itself to the president as he
 arrived in Philadelphia later in the day.
 Nevertheless, the president said Washington would use force if diplomacy
 fails to force Saddam Hussein to back down.
 The Russian foreign minister, meanwhile , sought to soften the harsh words
 of his military counterpart, saying on Friday that Russia now feels the
 US must hold off at least until UN secretary general Kofi Annan visits
 Baghdad in a last-ditch effort at diplomacy.
 Annan has no trip planned so far.
 Meanwhile, secretary of state Madeleine Albright, Berger and defense
 secretary William Cohen announced plans to travel to an unnamed city
 in the US heartland next week, to explain to the American people just why
 military force will be necessary if diplomacy fails.
 Steve Hurst, CNN, the state department.

</TEXT>
</section>

</BODY>































































































































































</TimeML>
