
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> ea980120.1830.0071 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="broadcast news"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<BODY>

<section endTime="187.815" startTime="71.235" type="report">
<TEXT>

 Good evening from the central park in downtown Havana. We are here this week to witness the rendezvous that Fidel Castro and the Pope  are having with history. 

 We are here because what happens on this island will also have an impact on the United States. Everything that happens in Cuba gets America's attention. 

 Incidentally, we just show up  to do the broadcast, and Cubans want  to know what we 're going  to tell Americans, in many cases, what their relatives in the United States  are going  to hear. 

 Well, this is the eve of the Pope's visit to one of the last bastions of Communism anywhere in the world, and it  is  already causing enormous expectations.

 In Revolution Square, they put up a giant cross today. And right across from the Cuban revolutionary icon Che Guevara, they now have a giant portrait of Jesus. Above it in Spanish, Jesus, in you we believe. 

 Not all Cubans believe, but Castro  has invited everyone  to welcome the man who has been one of Communism's most effective adversaries, and that's why there is suspense.

 Everyone appears  to believe that somehow Cuba  is going  to change. Castro  has said officially that it's okay to be enthusiastic. And so, people are increasingly enthusiastic by the day- 

 [[NS]]

 Today, Cuban television, which clings to the Communist Party line, actually began  to promote its papal coverage.

 Today, hundreds of people from the US began  to arrive, including some Cuban Americans who left here when Castro came  to power and  are returning to Havana for the first time. The Pope's visit is important, but they  are  also coming home.

 This is quite an extraordinary story unfolding here. We'll come back to Havana later in the broadcast.

 But now we 're going  to go back to New York, where Diane Sawyer has the rest of the news. Diane?
</TEXT></section></BODY>

































































































</TimeML>
