
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> NYT19980424.0421 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/24/1998 21:49:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
A3813 Cx1f taf-z
u k Cx13  Cx11  BC-EDIT-GENDER-STEREOTYP     04-24 0430
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-EDIT-GENDER-STEREOTYPES-NYT 
<HEADLINE>
EDITORIAL: THE COURT RETREATS ON STEREOTYPES
</HEADLINE>
UR (af) LR  QL
UR c.1998 N.Y. Times News Service QC  LR  QL

<TEXT>
The New York Times said in an editorial on Saturday, April 25:
The Supreme Court took a detour this week from the core
principle of gender fairness it vindicated two years ago in its
ruling invalidating the use of sexual stereotypes  to justify
denying women admission to the Virginia Military Institute. By a
6-3 vote, the court upheld a discriminatory immigration law that
gives a child born overseas to an unmarried American woman a better
chance at citizenship than a child born to an unmarried American
man.
Under the statute, a child born abroad to an unwed American
mother  is  automatically considered a U.S. citizen. But the child of
an unwed American father has no citizenship rights unless the
father takes the affirmative step of acknowledging paternity and
formally agrees  to provide support until the child turns 18.
The majority's views  were expressed in three separate opinions,
the most disquieting of which  was written by a liberal member,
Justice John Paul Stevens, and joined by a conservative, Chief
Justice William Rehnquist. The opinion, which found the gender
distinction reasonable, relied heavily on outmoded generalities
about family roles, including the flawed presumption that mothers
have a closer relationship to their children than fathers do. As
Justice Stephen Breyer asked in a strong dissent, ``what sense does
it make''  to apply citizenship barriers ``only to fathers and not
to mothers in today's world _ where paternity can  readily be proved
and where women and men both are likely  to earn a living in the
workplace?''
Justices Sandra Day O'Connor and Anthony Kennedy seemed to agree
that the law amounted to unconstitutional sex discrimination. Butinstead of providing the votes  to strike it down, they chose  to uphold it on the flimsy ground that because the sex of the parent
and not the child made the difference under the law, the plaintiff
did not have standing  to bring the case. The Justice Department,
which supported the statute, did not cover itself with glory
either. The department retreated from its position in the VMI case
when it argued that the government could not make policy based on
stereotypes ``even when those stereotypes reflect current
realities.''
As for the court, it managed with its splintered ruling  to cast
doubt both on the constitutionality of the immigration provisions
it upheld and on its true commitment to fighting gender
stereotypes.
</TEXT>
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
NYT-04-24-98 2149EDT
</TRAILER>








































































</TimeML>
