
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> NYT19980402.0453 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 04/02/1998 22:52:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
A0786 ampCx1f taf-z
u a ampCx13  ampCx11  BC-NJ-WOMEN-MURDER-PROBE     04-02 0319
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-NJ-WOMEN-MURDER-PROBE-NYT 
<HEADLINE>
TASK FORCE TO STUDY CASES OF 14 SLAIN WOMEN
</HEADLINE>
(lb) ampQL
ampUR By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN ampLR  ampQC  ampQL
ampUR c.1998 N.Y. Times News Service ampLR  ampQC  ampQL

<TEXT>
NEWARK, N.J. _ A new Essex County task force began delving
Thursday into the slayings of 14 black women over the last five
years in the Newark area, as law-enforcement officials acknowledged
that they needed  to work harder  to solve the cases of murdered
women.
The police and prosecutors said they  had identified different
suspects in six of the cases and had yet to find any pattern
linking the killings or the victims, several of whom  were believed
to be prostitutes.
State, county and local law-enforcement officials  have expressed
concerns in recent months about a possible pattern of murdered
women and a disproportionate number of unsolved cases.
Citing an example, Sgt. Derek Glenn, a spokesman for the Newark
Police Department, said that of nine women who  had  been killed last
year, suspects  had  been arrested in only four cases. But over all,
arrests  were made in more than 60 percent of murder cases, he said.
Eight of the 14 killings since 1993 were already under
investigation by the Newark Police Department, Glenn said. Of the
eight victims, three  were stabbed, two  were strangled, two  were beaten to death and one  was asphyxiated, he said, and these
different methods of killing and other evidence seem  to indicate
that the eight cases are not related.
But with the task-force investigation just getting under way,
officials have been careful not to draw any firm conclusions,
leaving open the possibility of a serial killer in some of the
cases. There have been no arrests in any of the slayings.
``I have n't seen a pattern yet ,  '' said Patricia Hurt, the Essex
County prosecutor, who created the task force on Tuesday. ``The
type of lifestyle these women have is extremely dangerous,'' she
said.
</TEXT>
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
NYT-04-02-98 2252EST
</TRAILER>



























































































































</TimeML>
