
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> NYT19980206.0466 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/06/1998 22:29:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
A6982 Cx1f taf-z
u w Cx13  Cx11  BC-CLINTON-CURRIE-NYT LR      02-06 0277
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-CLINTON-CURRIE-NYT 
<HEADLINE>
STATEMENTS CONCERNING MRS. CURRIE
</HEADLINE>
UR (bl) LR  QL
UR c.1998 N.Y. Times News Service LR  QC   QL

<TEXT>
WASHINGTON _ Following are statements made Friday and Thursday
by Lawrence Wechsler, a lawyer for the White House secretary, Betty
Currie; the White House; White House spokesman Mike McCurry, and
President Clinton in response to an article in The New York Times
on Friday about her statements regarding a meeting with the
president:
Wechsler on Thursday
``Without commenting on the allegations raised in this article,
to the extent that there is any implication or suggestion that Mrs.
Currie was aware of any legal or ethical impropriety by anyone,
that implication or suggestion is entirely inaccurate.''
White House on Thursday
``For the past few weeks we 've  been subjected to false leaks
designed  to mislead both reporters and the American public. We're not going  to dignify the latest false leak with a response.''
McCurry on Friday
``I want to be absolutely clear, to the extent there is any
implication or the slightest suggestion that Mrs. Currie believes
that the President or anyone else tried  to influence her
recollection, that is absolutely false and a mischaracterization of
the facts. I  am shocked and dismayed by the numerous leaks
regarding Mrs. Currie's grand jury testimony.''
Clinton on Friday.
``Once again, I never asked anybody  to do anything but tell the
truth. I know about the stories today. I was pleased that Ms.
Currie's lawyers stated unambiguously this morning _ unambiguously
_ that she's not aware of any unethical conduct.
</TEXT>
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
NYT-02-06-98 2229EST
</TRAILER>



















































































































</TimeML>
