
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> AP900815-0044 </DOCNO>
AP-NR-<FILEID>08-15-90 1337EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-GulfRdp 8thLd-Writethru   08-15 1334</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf Rdp, 8th Ld-Writethru,a0605,1368</SECOND>
Saddam Seeks End To War With Iran; Bush To Urge Jordan To Close
Port
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 28th graf pvs, Crown Prince... to CORRECT spelling of
Hassan; pick up 29th graf pvs, `A CBS...'</NOTE>
LaserPhotos WX6,7,XSAV1,NY5,10,TOK1,XAAFB1,AMM1, LaserColor XAAFB1
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's Saddam Hussein, facing U.S. and Arab troops at the Saudi
border, today sought peace on another front by promising to
withdraw from Iranian territory and release soldiers captured
during the Iran-Iraq war.
   Also today, King Hussein of Jordan arrived in Washington seeking
to mediate the Persian Gulf crisis. President Bush on Tuesday said
the United States may extend its naval quarantine to Jordan's Red
Sea port of Aqaba to shut off Iraq's last unhindered trade route.
   In another mediation effort, the Soviet Union said today it had
sent an envoy to the Middle East on a series of stops to include
Baghdad. Soviet officials also said Soviet women, children and
invalids would be allowed to leave Iraq.
   President Bush today denounced Saddam's ``ruinous policies of
war,'' and said the United States is ``striking a blow for the
principle that might does not make right.''
   In a speech delivered at the Pentagon, Bush seemed to suggest
that American forces could be in the gulf region for some time.
``No one should doubt our staying power or determination,'' he said.
   The U.S. military buildup in Saudi Arabia continued at fever
pace, with Syrian troops now part of a multinational force camped
out in the desert to guard the Saudi kingdom from any new thrust by
Iraq.
   In a letter to President Hashemi Rafsanjani of Iran, read by a
broadcaster over Baghdad radio, Saddam said he will begin
withdrawing troops from Iranian territory on Friday and release
Iranian prisoners of war.
   Iran said an Iraqi diplomatic delegation was en route to Tehran
to deliver Saddam's message, which it said it would review ``with
optimism.''
   Saddam appeared to accept a border demarcation treaty he had
rejected in peace talks following the August 1988 cease-fire of the
eight-year war with Iran.
   The move seemed aimed at heading off more trouble with Iran,
which had condemned Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2 but also
criticized the multinational force dispatched to Saudi Arabia.
   Saddam said he sought to ``turn the gulf into a lake of peace
free of foreign fleets and forces that harbor ill intentions
against us.''
   In other developments:
   _The Pentagon said that Defense Secretary Dick Cheney is
considering urging Bush to order a national callup of armed forces
reserves for active duty because of the drain on units sending
soldiers abroad. Bush can call up to 200,000 reservists for up to
180 days without seeking congressional approval.
   _Soviet Foreign Ministry spokesman Yuri Gremitskikh said special
ambassador Mikhail Sytenko left Tuesday for consultations with the
governments of Syria, Jordan, Egypt and other Arab countries.
Sytenko, a former deputy secretary-general of the United Nations,
is also expected to visit Baghdad, Gremitskikh said at a regular
news briefing today.
   _The outlook darkened for about 3,000 Americans caught in Iraq
and Kuwait when Saddam sent his forces into the small, oil-rich
sultanate.
   The Iraqi ambassador to Greece said in Athens the Americans and
other stranded foreigners could leave ``as soon as the threats from
the United States and its allies are eliminated.'' ABC quoted an
Iraqi Foreign Ministry official in Baghdad as saying Americans in
Iraq are ``restrictees'' who will stay there until the crisis ends.
   _The Soviet Foreign Ministry said Soviet women, children and
invalids would be permitted to leave Iraq. Spokesman Yuri
Gremitskikh said the first group of 230 evacuees was assembling in
Baghdad today, but evacuation plans were hampered by desert heat
and lack of transportation.
   Nearly 9,000 Soviets were among the hundreds of thousands of
foreigners trapped in Iraq and Kuwait. Iraq has agreed to allow all
880 Soviets in Kuwait to leave, but only by a 1,200-mile road route
through Iraq and to the Iraq-Jordan border.
   _The British Foreign Office said today conditions in Kuwait
appear to be deteriorating. There have been reports of wholesale
looting but food and gasoline were <JG>still available</JG>, said a
spokesman, who by custom was not identified. Banks remained closed.
   _The Iraqi ambassador to Venezuela said on Tuesday that Iraq
would retaliate against Venezuela and other OPEC oil cartel members
if they boost oil production to fill the gap created by blocked
supplies from Iraq and Kuwait. With Kuwait now ``annexed,'' Iraq
has control of 20 percent of the world's oil reserves. A steep rise
in world oil prices followed the Kuwait invasion.
   The U.N. Security Council on Aug. 6 ordered a global embargo on
trade with Iraq as punishment for seizing Kuwait. Bush then sent
U.S. troops and planes to Saudi Arabia, saying Iraqi troops massed
<JG>nearby</JG> in Kuwait threatened Saudi Arabia and its vast oil reserves.
   Twelve Arab League nations voted for an Arab force to protect
Saudi Arabia, with the vanguard of Syria's contingent arriving
Tuesday, <IN-MW>according to</IN-MW> diplomatic sources in Riyadh, the Saudi
capital.
   Egyptian and Moroccan troops are already there.
   The predominantly Moslem nation of Bangladesh said today its
troops would join multinational forces in Saudi Arabia. The size of
the contingent was not disclosed.
   Turkey and Saudi Arabia in effect shut down Iraq's major oil
outlets through those countries, but <IN-MW>according to</IN-MW> Jordanian
officials, a smaller line into Jordan remained operating.
   Truckloads of goods rolled into Iraq from Jordan on Tuesday and
Iraqi-bound cargo was <JG>unloaded</JG> from ships at the Red Sea port
ofAqaba despite the U.N.-ordered sanctions.
   King Hussein was reportedly carrying a message to Bush from
Iraq's Saddam, with whom the king met Monday. The monarch will meet
Bush on Thursday in Kennebunkport, Maine.
   Crown Prince Hassan, King Hussein's brother and political
adviser, was asked today about the message the king was said to be
carrying. In an interview from Jordan on ABC, he declined to
discuss details, but said: ``I don't think that his majesty would
be traveling at this crucial moment if the Iraqi leadership did not
have a rational approach to the future.''
   A CBS News report citing unidentified Jordanian sources said
that Saddam's message called for an international conference to be
convened to discuss an Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait. In exchange,
the buildup of U.S. forces in the region would halt. Bush, however,
says he sees no short-term hope for a diplomatic solution to the
gulf crisis _ at least until economic sanctions force Saddam to
withdraw his army.
   Bush held out the prospect of more aid to Jordan if it
cooperates with the trade embargo.
   On Tuesday, the United States and Soviet Union conferred in
Washington on putting an anti-Iraq naval blockade under a United
Nations umbrella.
   The United States has provided <JG>most</JG> of the naval vessels so far
to block Iraqi trade, with Britain, West Germany and Australia
among the other nations lending support at sea.
   The embargo is meant to cripple Iraq by cutting off its exports
of oil and imports of food and military supplies. Iraq imports
about three-quarters of its foodstuffs.
   U.S. allies and other U.N. members have objected that the
Security Council embargo resolution did not specifically authorize
<JG>such</JG> a naval operation.
   Bush told a news conference on Tuesday that the naval barricade
now in force might be extended to Jordan's Aqaba ``if it is a hole
through which commerce flows'' in and out of Iraq.
   In Saudi Arabia, today is the eighth day of ``Desert Shield,''
the operation designed to confront an estimated 200,000 Iraqi
soldiers now in Kuwait. Iraq boasts an army of 1 million members.
At least 50,000 U.S. troops are expected to be committed to Desert
Shield within weeks, including Marines, Army air assault forces,
paratroopers and infantry.
   Iraq said it invaded Kuwait because of disputes over oil and
money. It accused Kuwait of deliberately slashing Iraqi oil
revenues by overproducing oil and driving down prices, among other
charges.
   Iraq has 17 million residents, and Kuwait about 1.9 million.
</TEXT>

























































































































































































































































































































































































































































































































</TimeML>
