
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> AP900816-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-16-90 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0723 08-16 1350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0723,1392</SECOND>
Gulf Showdown Takes More Personal Tack: Saddam Calls Bush a `Liar'
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to RECAST, ADDS background on oil reserves,
food imports, UPDATES with State Department reax to Saddam, EDITS
to trim. No pickup</NOTE>
LaserPhotos
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Persian Gulf showdown between Iraq and the United States
took a more personal turn Thursday when Iraq's Saddam Hussein
called President Bush a liar and said the outbreak of holy war
could bring thousands of Americans home in coffins.
   Bush, commenting on the two-week-old gulf crisis from his
vacation home in Maine, said he saw little reason to be optimistic
about a settlement of the dispute, which stems from Iraq's invasion
of oil-wealthy Kuwait and its subsequent military buildup on the
border of Saudi Arabia.
   After a two-hour meeting at his Kennebunkport home with King
Hussein of Jordan, Bush said, ``I did not come away with any
feeling of hope'' that Iraq would withdraw its army from Kuwait.
   Bush also said Thursday that King Hussein assured him Jordan
would close the last remaining free port to most Iraqi trade as the
economic embargo on materials to Iraq continued unabated.
Foodstuffs are among the goods  being blocked from entry; Iraq
imports about three-quarters of its food.
   Pentagon sources in Washington meanwhile said the Bush
administration plans  to deploy 45,000 Marines to the region to back
up the thousands of Army, Navy and Air Force troops already in
place in the gulf and the Saudi desert.
   At a news conference, Secretary of State James A. Baker III said
Jordan `` is seeking some guidance'' about a provision in the
U.N.-backed trade embargo that allows food for humanitarian
purposes.
   Worries however grew about the safety of Americans and other
Westerners trapped in Kuwait. Iraqi military authorities ordered
all Americans and Britons in Kuwait  to assemble at a hotel,
officials said.
   ``Very few'' of the 2,500 Americans in occupied Kuwait complied
with the order, a senior U.S. official told The Associated Press.
   Iraq said the roundup was  to protect them from unspecified
threats; British Foreign Office minister William Waldegrave called
the order ``grave and sinister.''
   ``What we fear is that they  will  be interned somewhere, most
likely in Iraq,'' Waldegrave said.
   A total of about 3,000 Americans, 3,000 Britons and more than
450 Japanese are in Iraq and Kuwait. Overall, more than 2 million
foreigners are in both countries. Iraq  has called them
``restrictees.''
   In addition to the estimated 45,000 Marines to ultimately be
part of Operation Desert Shield, Stealth fighter planes and the
aircraft carrier John F. Kennedy  are  also headed to Saudi Arabia  to protect it from Iraqi expansionism.
   In Washington, Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams said Iraq  has continued  to increase its armed forces in Kuwait and they now
number about 160,000.
   Saddam has been under international quarantine since his Aug. 2
power-grab, or what he calls an ``eternal merger'' with Kuwait.
   In a long verbal attack read on Iraqi television Thursday,
Saddam repeatedly called Bush ``a liar'' and said a shooting war
could produce body bags courtesy of Baghdad.
   ``We continue  to pray and pray hard to God so that there will be
no confrontation whereby you  will receive thousands of Americans
wrapped in sad coffins after you  had pushed them into a dark
tunnel,'' Saddam said.
   He called U.S. soldiers massing in Saudi Arabia the real
occupiers in the Persian Gulf.
   Replied State Department deputy spokesman Richard Boucher, ``We
have n't  really analyzed the statement in detail but it appears to
be just another example of his outlandish rhetoric and his attempts
 to distort the truth.
   ``We believe that his words cannot distract the world from the
facts of Iraqi aggression.''
   An international land, sea and air force  has mobilized since
Iraq's invasion, which  was sparked by disputes over oil, land and
repayment of war loans.
   In the largest U.S. military operation since Vietnam, an
estimated 20,000 American GIs  have  already massed  to defend Saudi
Arabia.
   ``We  do n't  just arrive,'' said four-star Gen. John Dailey,
assistant commandant of the U.S. Marine Corps. ``We're there to stay for a fairly lengthy period.''
   Egypt, Syria, Morocco and Bangladesh also committed ground
troops, to a much lesser degree.
   The U.S. Navy has 27 ships in the maritime barricade of Iraq.
They  are aided by Britain, West Germany, Australia, Canada, the
Netherlands and Belgium. Bush  was expected  to authorize naval
commanders  to use ``the minimum force necessary''  to interdict
shipments to and from Iraq, a U.S. official said. That 
could    include firing across the bow to halt a ship.
   In the air, U.S. Air Force fliers say they  have engaged in ``a
little cat and mouse'' with Iraqi warplanes, which  have retreated
when weapons radar locks onto them. ``They  do n't want  to play with
us,'' one U.S. crew chief said.
   In Kuwait, the Iraqis  have rimmed the capital city with an
air-defense system, according to a U.S. official who spoke on the
condition of anonymity. He declined to say if the weapons included
missiles, but the Iraqis have them in their arsenal. The Iraqis
also possess chemical weapons.
   The combined operations  are designed  to isolate and strangle
Iraq until it retreats from Kuwait. The quarantine hopes  to staunch
the flow of Iraqi oil, which is Iraq's economic lifeblood, and
clamp down on food and supplies going in.
   Iraq now controls 20 percent of the world's oil reserves with
its conquest of Kuwait. Only Saudi Arabia has more oil reserves.
   The economic chokehold appears  to  be working.
   The Lloyd's List International newspaper, which monitors
worldwide shipping, said Iraq's fleet of 80 tankers and cargo ships
 has stopped regular trading.
   John Prescott, a shipping correspondent, said there was no
shipping in Kuwaiti or Iraqi ports and that activity  was trailing off in the Jordanian port of Aqaba.
   Bush's chief objective in his meeting with Hussein was to press
the king  to shut down Iraq's food and oil supply route from Aqaba
on the Red Sea.
   Aqaba is Iraq's only outlet now that an international noose  has tightened. Bush  has indicated the U.S. Navy  will barricade the port
from Iraqi ships. The president also has offered  to help offset
Jordan's costs because 40 percent of its exports go to Iraq and 90
percent of its oil comes from there.
   ``It's our only outlet to the sea and the rest of the world,''
Hussein said. He also said of trade with Iraq: ``There are no
shipments at the moment.''
   A day earlier, scores of trucks, many with Iraqi license plates,
streamed north out of Aqaba to Amman and onto the desert highway
bound for Iraq.
   The Jordanian monarch met this week with Saddam, but he told
reporters he had no message from Baghdad. ``I am not talking on
behalf of anyone in the area ... but myself,'' Hussein said.
   In the United Nations, Libya called for the replacement of U.S.
forces in the Persian Gulf with Arab League forces and U.N.
soldiers.
   Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi, in a letter to the U.N.
Secretary-General, also called for an emergency Security Council
meeting in Geneva  to remove U.S. forces. There was no decision on a
meeting.
   Thirty-two of the 159 U.N. members  had filed compliance reports
by Wednesday, and all  were honoring the sanctions Iraq.
   Also Thursday, Saudi Arabia called for an emergency conference
of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries  to discuss how
much oil  to pump.
   The minister denied the kingdom had notified notified any of its
customers of any cutbacks in oil supply. Reports attributed to the
Japanese foreign ministry said Saudi Arabia told U.S., European and
Japanese oil companies of a 15-20 percent cutback in its oil supply
in September.
   Meanwhile, Egypt's official Middle East News Agency said
Thursday that Saddam was the target of an assassination attempt,
which led to ``large-scale'' arrests, including some close
associates of the Iraqi strongman.
   The agency quoted witnesses as saying tanks and armored cars are
patrolling the streets of Baghdad. There was no independent
confirmation of the report by the government-run news agency, which
did not say when the reported attempt occurred.
</TEXT>


















































































































































































































































































































































































































































































</TimeML>
