
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980322.0749 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/22/1998 14:57:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1834 Cx1f wstm-
r i Cx13  Cx11  BC-NorthernIreland 1stLd-Writethru   03-22 0720
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Northern Ireland, 1st Ld-Writethru 
<HEADLINE>
Police find bomb on eve of Sinn Fein's return to peace talks
</HEADLINE>
UR Eds: NEW throughout; RAISES reference to bomb; UPDATES with protest
against Protestant marches, comment from Sinn Fein leader; trims
pvs QL
UR By SHAWN POGATCHNIK QC
UR Associated Press Writer QC

<TEXT>
BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) _ Police seized a car bomb under
construction Sunday in a town bordering Northern Ireland on the eve
of the return to peace talks by the IRA-allied Sinn Fein party.
Chief Superintendent Al McHugh said the bomb discovered in the
Irish Republic was destined for an unknown target in Northern
Ireland and ``would have caused massive destruction.''
The discovery appeared to be the latest attempt by extremists
opposed to the IRA's 8-month-old truce to undermine the peace
process, set to resume Monday in Belfast.
Extremists have bombed two predominantly pro-British Protestant
towns and fired mortar shells at a police station since Sinn Fein
was expelled from peace talks on Feb. 20 in punishment for two
killings blamed on the Irish Republican Army.
Police found more than 1,300 pounds (600 kgs) of
fertilizer-based explosives Sunday in a shed in Dundalk, 50 miles
(80 kms) south of Belfast.
They arrested two men in connection with the bomb factory, which
also contained circuitry, detonating cord and the Mitsubishi truck
that would have carried the bomb.
The British and Irish governments, which cosponsor the
multi-party talks that are supposed to conclude by May, invited
Sinn Fein to rejoin two weeks ago.
But Sinn Fein leader Gerry Adams kept his party out pending
meetings with British Prime Minister Tony Blair 10 days ago and
President Clinton last week.
``We were unjustly pushed out of the talks in February but we
are back,'' Adams said Sunday.
He said the north's substantial Catholic minority demanded a
settlement that would promote Northern Ireland's eventual
unification with the Irish Republic.
``Nationalists in the north are not  a minority in someone else's
country. We are Irish citizens, living in our own country,'' Adams
said, adding: ``Nationalists want to move towards Irish unity and
see this process as a bridge in that direction.''
But the north's pro-British Protestant majority is bitterly opposed to uniting Ireland and instead wants a strong government
for Northern Ireland, which has been ruled directly by London since
1972.
Northern Ireland's biggest Protestant party, the Ulster
Unionists, is threatening to push for Sinn Fein's expulsion once
again. They say IRA commanders are responsible for the recent bomb
attacks.
Also Sunday, more than 2,000 Catholic protesters rallied in
Portadown against the annual parades by the Orange Order, Northern
Ireland's dominant Protestant fraternal group.
Confrontations among Catholic protesters, Protestant marchers
and the police have provoked widespread violence in Northern
Ireland for the <COMMENT NOTE="not sure how to capture this so annotated it as 3 years">past three summers</COMMENT>. The crucible is Portadown, 30
miles (50 kms) southwest of Belfast, where Orangemen march each
July from their rural church back downtown _ through the town's
main Catholic area.
Protesters from several Catholic communities crowded into
Portadown's Catholic Garvaghy Road to hear speakers demand
negotiations with Orange Order leaders, and pledge to participate
in each others' road-blocking protests this summer.
``Small nationalist communities are not going to be left on
their own this summer,'' said Gerard Rice, a former IRA prisoner
who leads anti-Orange protests in a Catholic neighborhood of south
Belfast.
Riot police in armored cars, shields and helmets prevented a few
hundred Protestants, many waving British and Ulster flags, from
interfering with the Catholics as they marched within Portadown's
few Catholic streets.
Earlier Sunday, police and militant Protestants clashed in a
religiously polarized part of north Belfast.
Police said an unmarked police car was hit with gasoline bombs
from the Protestant side. Riot police responded with a volley of
plastic bullets that scattered a 50-strong mob.
An elderly Catholic man was hospitalized from cuts after a
Protestant gasoline bomb landed in his back yard. Police arrested
six Protestants on suspicion of rioting.
(sp/eml)
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Northern Ireland, 1st Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-22-98 1457EST
</TRAILER>


















































































































































































</TimeML>
