
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980308.0201 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 03/08/1998 06:26:00</DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2106 Cx1f wstm-
r i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kos     03-08 0243
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kosovo,0242 
<HEADLINE>
Ethnic Albanians in Turkey protest Serb attacks in Kosovo
</HEADLINE>
UR AP Photos IST101-102 QL

<TEXT>
ISTANBUL, Turkey (AP) _ Some 1,500 ethnic Albanians marched
Sunday in downtown Istanbul, burning Serbian flags to protest the
killings of ethnic Albanians by Serb police in southern Serb Kosovo
province.
The police barred the crowd from reaching the Yugoslavian
consulate in downtown Istanbul, but allowed them to demonstrate on
nearby streets.
``Stop the bloodshed in Kosovo,'' the protesters chanted.
Meanwhile in the capital, Ankara, a few hundred ethnic Albanians
laid a black wreath at the gate of Yugoslavian embassy.
Ethnic Albanians comprise 90 percent of the population in
Kosovo, but Serbs maintain control through a large military and
police presence. Serbian police say they are trying to eliminate
the pro-independence Kosovo Liberation Army and restore order.
At least 51 people were reported killed in clashes between Serb
police and ethnic Albanians in the troubled region in recent days.
Turkey, worried about civil war in Kosovo spilling to the whole
Balkans, urged all Balkan states to sign a joint declaration that
the Kosovo crisis be solved peacefully and without any change of
borders.
Turks feel they have special ties to the whole region, which
they ruled for hundreds of years during the Ottoman Empire. They
also share Islam with the ethnic Albanians.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Turkey-Yugoslavia-Kosovo; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:MEST;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-03-08-98 0626EST
</TRAILER>


































































</TimeML>
