
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980213.1310 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/13/1998 14:26:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2112 Cx1f wstm-
r i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Australia-Republic 4thLd-Writethru   02-13 0603
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Australia-Republic, 4th Ld-Writethru,0602 
<HEADLINE>
Constitutional convention votes for republic, against links to
</HEADLINE>
British monarchy QL
UR Eds: ADDS 2 grafs at end with reaction from former prime minister
Paul Keating QL
UR AP Photo CANB101,102,103 QL
UR By ALAN THORNHILL QC
UR Associated Press Writer QC

<TEXT>
CANBERRA, Australia (AP) _ Turning its back on 210 years of
loyalty to the British royal family, a constitutional convention
voted overwhelmingly Friday to make Australia a republic under its
own president.
Prime Minister John Howard, a monarchist himself, promised to put the question to a national referendum next year after
convention delegates voted 89-52 for a republic, with 11
abstentions.
Spontaneous applause echoed through the chamber and public
galleries as the crucial vote passed by a wide margin.
``I want a referendum,'' Howard said. ``The Australian people
are owed the opportunity of expressing an opinion on this.''
``It would be a travesty in common sense terms of Australian
democracy for that proposition not to be put to the Australian
people,'' Howard said.
Even in his own Cabinet, Howard is becoming increasingly isolated with his monarchist stance. Treasurer Peter Costello,
Environment Minister Robert Hill and Attorney General Daryl
Williams all voted to support the republic Friday.
``This convention will be seen as a turning point in our
history,'' Australian Republican Movement spokeswoman Mary
Delahunty said.
Pro-republicans hope to have an Australian president by the
opening of the 2000 Olympics and the 100th anniversary of
Australian federation.
Calling for an amended constitution with a new preamble, to be written by Australian poets, republican Janet Holmes a Court said,
``We need the smell of eucalyptus in this, and the feel of red
dust.''
Monarchists hope to defeat the republic at the referendum.
``The phony war has finished and the real referendum campaign
has clearly begun,'' Australians for a Constitutional Monarchy
executive director Kerry Jones said.
``Well may  we say  `God save the Queen,' for nothing will save
the republic,'' outraged monarchist delegate David Mitchell said.
``The idea of a republic will fall to dust through the grace of
almighty God.''
Polls have shown public support for a republic increasing,
rising from about 35 percent several years ago to about 51 percent
this year, as pro-monarchist sentiment diminishes.
Australia has been independent since 1901, but like many
Commonwealth nations it still recognizes the British monarch as its
head of state.
Howard said Queen Elizabeth II is taking a great interest in the
convention.
``She is, I can assure you, from what I've been told, she's following the thing very closely and taking the view it's our
business.
``It's no secret that she's indicated to me ... she is a 20th
century democrat, understands that the role of the crown in
Australia rests in the hands of the Australian people as it has for
almost a hundred years.''
The model for a republic, adopted over bitter objections from
those advocating direct election of a president, is for
presidential nominations to be made with public input and the
winning candidate decided by a two-thirds majority of Parliament.
Former prime minister Paul Keating, who put the republic issue
in the spotlight in his unsuccessful 1996 campaign for re-election,
welcomed the result.
``This is an important step along the path towards Australia
claiming its full sovereignty, and due recognition that the
monarchy can no longer serve us appropriately,'' Keating said.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Australia-Republic, 4th Ld-Writethru; CT:i;
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-13-98 1426EST
</TRAILER>

























































































































































































</TimeML>
