
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980227.0487 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/27/1998 08:09:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2392 Cx1f wstm-
u i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Israel-Rabin     02-27 0300
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Israel-Rabin,0300 
<HEADLINE>
Friend of Rabin's assassin regretted praying for Rabin's death
</HEADLINE>
UR By DANNA HARMAN QC
UR Associated Press Writer QC

<TEXT>
JERUSALEM (AP) _ Taking the stand in her own defense, a friend
of Yitzhak Rabin's assassin said Friday that she regretted calling
the prime minister a traitor and praying for his death.
Margalit Har-Shefi, 22, has pleaded <JG>innocent</JG> to charges that she
failed to report Yigal Amir's plan to kill Rabin. She took the
stand for more than four hours Friday in a Tel Aviv magistrate's
court.
Amir, 27, is serving a life sentence for the November 1995
assassination of Rabin at a Tel Aviv peace rally. Newspaper reports
have said Amir was infatuated with Har-Shefi and may have been
trying to impress her by killing the prime minister.
Har-Shefi acknowledged she told police interrogators that Rabin
was a traitor and that she prayed for him to have a heart attack
and die. She said Rabin's murder was ``a black stain on Israel,''
Israel radio and Israel army radio reported.
Har-Shefi said she heard Amir talk about killing Rabin but did
not tell the police because she did not believe he was <JG>serious</JG>.
Instead, she turned to her community rabbi in the Jewish West Bank
settlement of Beit El and told him about Amir's statements. The
rabbi said called the talk about killing Rabin ``nonsense,'' and
said Jews are prohibited from killing one another, the radio
reports said.
Har-Shefi described Amir as an ``original thinker,'' as well as
delusional and a liar.
She also denied accusations made by Amir's brother, Hagai, that
she joined an anti-Arab underground movement. She said she gave the
Amir brothers false information regarding the location of a weapons
and ammunition cache when they asked her to help organize such a
movement.
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Israel-Rabin; CT:i;
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:INDI;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:ASIA;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-27-98 0809EST
</TRAILER>



































































































































</TimeML>
