
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980501.0480 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 05/01/1998 09:13:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w2844 Cx1f wstm-
r w Cx13  Cx11  SETTING-THE-STAGEsked     05-01 0665
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 SETTING-THE-STAGE sked 
<HEADLINE>
MALAYSIA
Setting the stage for Net convergence, NEW STRAITS TIMES-MANAGEMENT TIMES </HEADLINE>
QL
xfdws SETTING-THE-STAGE sked
Emerging Markets Datafile
April 30, 1998
NEW STRAITS TIMES-MANAGEMENT TIMES
ENGLISH
COPYRIGHT 1998 BY WORLDSOURCES, INC., A JOINT VENTURE OF FDCH,
INC. AND WORLD TIMES, INC. NO PORTION OF THE MATERIALS CONTAINED
HEREIN MAY BE USED
IN ANY MEDIA WITHOUT ATTRIBUTION TO WORLDSOURCES, INC.
<TEXT>
MALAYSIA'S aggressive move into the information age could not come in a more opportune time.
With the convergence of communications and information
technologies (IT) coupled with the coming of age for the Internet
and its related technologies, the stage is set for Malaysians to seize the chance to transform into a knowledge society and become
worthy opponents/players in the global market space.
The Internet, the global network of computers, is now far reaching into the country - extending its embrace to include every
nook and cranny of the nation - opening doors to not only a diverse
range of information sources but also an exhaustive list of
possibilities to create new applications which add value to
people's lives.
In the business world, the Internet - through intranet and
extranet solutions - has become an invaluable tool for companies to
harness so as to gain a competitive edge.
The solutions are also vital components in developing the
borderless marketing flagship application which is a vital element
for spearheading the development of the Multimedia Super Corridor
(MSC) project.
The application will create the necessary framework and
infrastructure to support electronic commerce (e-commerce)
initiatives in the country.
However, it is important to note that installing or implementing
Internet technologies for technology's sake would not ensure
instant success.
For e-commerce to flourish with full-blown end-to-end business
transactions, strategic planning which incorporates both business
and technology plans that are complementary is necessary for an
organisation to see feasible returns on investment.
Intranets, through the use of Internet technology, are positioned as a platform for companies to optimise, expand and
transform new channels of business.
When strategically implemented, an intranet solution will provide the ability to mediate mission-critical, decision support
functions in organisations. It will also help further improve
communications and collaboration at all levels in an organisation.
With intranets in place, it is only logical for organisations to
respectively link the network to other companies' for extended
business purposes through extranets.
While this will enable the sharing of information among
enterprises, security issues such as firewalls and encryption as
well as access and control procedures, and the trust levels that
enterprises have with each other will emerge and there will be a
need to address them.
Other than usage in business, Internet technology is also beginning to infiltrate the lifestyle domain. ``Smart homes'' have emerged bringing a wealth of information and entertainment to
families over telecommunications lines.
The art of socialising is also experiencing a change where
Net/virtual relationships are fast overtaking or becoming parallel
with the normal human relationships.
Whether this would prove positive or otherwise towards society
in the future is yet to be seen.
All in all, the Internet has a lot to offer. However, its value
and benefits are only as good as how we use it.

</TEXT>
Copyright 1998 NEW STRAITS TIMES-MANAGEMENT TIMES all rights
reserved as distributed by WorldSources, Inc.
(PROFILE
(WS SL:SETTING-THE-STAGE sked; CT:w;
(REG:ENGL;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-05-01-98 0913EDT
</TRAILER>



















































































































































</TimeML>
