
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> APW19980219.0476 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/19/1998 08:02:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
w1151 Cx1f wstm-
r i Cx13  Cx11  BC-Cambodia-Britain-Host     02-19 0690
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-Cambodia-Britain-Hostage 
<HEADLINE>
Cambodian resistance general looking for remains of missing Briton
</HEADLINE>
 UR By DON PATHAN QC 
 UR Associated Press Writer QC 

<TEXT>
	   O'SMACH, Cambodia (AP) _ The top commander of a Cambodian
resistance force said Thursday he has sent a team to recover the
remains of a British mine removal expert kidnapped and presumed
killed by Khmer Rouge guerrillas almost two years ago.
	   Gen. Nhek Bunchhay, a loyalist of ousted Cambodian Prime
Minister Prince Norodom Ranariddh, said in an interview with The
Associated Press at his hilltop headquarters that he hopes to recover the remains of Christopher Howes within the next two weeks.
	   Howes had been working for the Britain-based Mines Advisory
Group when he was abducted with his Cambodian interpreter Houn
Hourth in March 1996. There were many conflicting accounts of his
fate.
	   Howes' team was clearing mines 17 kilometers (10 miles) from
Angkor Wat, the fabled 11th century temple that is Cambodia's main
tourist attraction, when it was attacked.
	   In January this year, British police officers who had been searching for Howes concluded he had probably been killed soon
after being captured.
	   The Foreign Office said it had informed the family of Howes, 37
years old when he was kidnapped, that he probably died within weeks
or months of his capture on March 26, 1996.
	   ``Obviously, it is deeply discouraging for the family after 22
months, but there is no proof of life. But there is no evidence in
either direction _ that there is proof of life or death,'' said a
Foreign Office spokesman, speaking with customary anonymity. ``We
will continue to do everything we can  to establish what has happened.''
	   Thai military officials who monitor Cambodian affairs said privately Thursday that Britain, through its embassies in Thailand
and Cambodia, has been pushing hard to resolve the Howes case as
the second anniversary of his abduction nears.
	   Nhek Bunchhay, who had been closely involved in the search for
Howes before having to flee the Cambodian capital after a coup
d'etat last year, appeared confident he would find Howes' remains.
	   He said he received information from Khmer Rouge guerrillas on
where the body had been buried, and recently ordered 10 of his men
from a force of 500 near Khmer Rouge headquarters in Anlong Veng to conduct the search.
	   If and when the remains are found, he said, they would be turned
over to the British Embassy, apparently meaning they would be sent
across the border into Thailand and onward to Bangkok.
	   Nhek Bunchhay said he now believed Howes had been killed within
a week of his capture by a Khmer Rouge faction loyal to Pol Pot,
then the guerrilla group's leader. Pol Pot is considered
responsible for the radical policies that led to the deaths of as
many as 1.7 million Cambodians when the communist group held power
in the late 1970s.
	   At the time Howes was captured, the Khmer Rouge were a more or
less united guerrilla force with more than 10,000 men under arms.
But the group began to fall apart in mid-1996 after the defection
of one of its top leaders, Ieng Sary. Other commanders, and
thousands of guerrillas, followed him.
	   A small hardcore group under Pol Pot continued to hold out at
their headquarters at Anlong Veng in northern Cambodia near the
Thai border.
	   But in June last year, the remaining leadership had a falling
out, and Pol Pot was arrested.
	   In July last year in Phnom Penh, Cambodia's capital, Second
Prime Minister Hun Sen staged a successful coup d'etat against
First Prime Minister Prince Norodom Ranariddh. Ranariddh's
loyalists, including Nhek Bunchhay, his top military commander,
went into hiding or fled the capital.
	   Nhek Bunchhay, evading an intensive manhunt, made his way to
O'Smach, the last major outpost held by Ranariddh's forces. His men
have held the stronghold _ which is on the border just opposite the
Thai province of Surin _ against repeated intense attacks by Hun
Sen's troops. They have been aided by Khmer Rouge guerrillas from
Anlong Veng, who have formed an alliance with Ranariddh's
resistance forces to oppose Hun Sen. 	   
</TEXT>
(PROFILE
(WS SL:BC-Cambodia-Britain-Hostage; CT:i; 
(REG:ASIA;)
(REG:ENGL;)
(REG:EURO;)
(REG:BRIT;)
(REG:SCAN;)
(REG:MEST;)
(REG:AFRI;)
(REG:INDI;)
(LANG:ENGLISH;))
)
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
AP-NY-02-19-98 0802EST
</TRAILER>














































































































































































































</TimeML>
