
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> NYT19980206.0460 </DOCNO>
<DOCTYPE SOURCE="newswire"> NEWS STORY </DOCTYPE>
<DATE_TIME> 02/06/1998 22:19:00 </DATE_TIME>
<HEADER>
A6974 Cx1f tta-z
u f Cx13  Cx11  BC-ECON-REPORT-ART-NYT LR      02-06 0974
</HEADER>
<BODY>
 BC-ECON-REPORT-ART-NYT 
<HEADLINE>
(REPEATING to correct coding)
</HEADLINE>
UR JANUARY JOB TOTALS UP AT A ROBUST CLIP LR  QL
UR (ART ADV: Graphic is being sent to NYT graphic clients.
Non-subscribers can make individual purchase by calling
212-556-4204.) LR  QL
UR (JT LR ) QL
UR By RICHARD W. STEVENSON LR  QC   QL
UR c.1998 N.Y. Times News Service LR  QC   QL

<TEXT>
WASHINGTON _ The economy created jobs at a surprisingly robust
pace in January, the government reported on Friday, evidence that
America's economic stamina has withstood any disruptions caused so far by the financial tumult in Asia.
The Bureau of Labor Statistics said the economy added 358,000
jobs last month, far above the 235,000 forecast by economists.
It was the third consecutive month that job generation has been
exceptionally strong. With growing opportunities for work drawing
more people into the labor force, the unemployment rate remained at
4.7 percent last month, just a notch above its quarter-century low.
The demand for workers also led employers to raise wages again
last month. Average hourly earnings of production and
nonsupervisory employees rose 4 cents, to $12.51. The gain left
wages 3.8 percent higher than a year earlier, extending a trend
that has given back to workers some of the earning power they lost
to inflation in the last decade.
But economists said the wage increase was not enough to raise
any concerns about higher inflation. And because the Federal
Reserve has made clear that it expects the economy to slow in
coming months as ripple effects from Asia reach the United States,
investors disregarded the large jobs gains, betting that neither a
rise in interest rates nor resurgent inflation is looming.
Stocks rose, pushing the Dow Jones industrial average up 72.24
points, to 8,189.49, leaving the index within 70 points of its
record high set on Aug. 6. In the bond market, a sensitive
barometer of inflation anxiety, prices edged up , pushing down the
yield on the benchmark 30-year Treasury bond to 5.92 percent from
5.93 percent.
``Job creation is sturdy and we have effective price
stability,'' said Paul McCulley, an economist at UBS Securities.
``The bottom line is that we've got a lovely economy.''
With potential inflation counterbalanced by worries about
possible price declines, the Fed and its chairman, Alan Greenspan,
have suggested that they intend to keep interest rates unchanged
until the economy tilts clearly in one direction or another.
The job figures for January extended a surge in employment gains
that began last fall, just when the labor market had showed signs
of cooling. After accounting for a small downward revision Friday
to December's figures, the economy has been creating jobs at a rate
of 358,000 a month for the last four months _ and 381,000 over the
last three months _ after averaging 242,000 for the first nine
months of 1997.
The surge in jobs reflects a remarkable confluence of positive
and self-reinforcing economic forces. Inflation has been almost
nonexistent, and consumer confidence has been extremely strong.
After a short, sharp drop when Asia's financial problems first
became clear, the stock market has rebounded and corporate profits
have remained healthy.
Long-term interest rates, an important indicator of economic
stability, have fallen in the last few months. Lower rates have helped invigorate housing and other interest-sensitive sectors of
the economy by making loans more affordable, and have allowed
companies to continue investing heavily in more efficient
equipment.
The likelihood that the federal budget will soon move from
deficit into surplus has further improved the outlook. The less
money the government needs to borrow, the more is freed for private
investment.
President Clinton welcomed the job figures at a news conference
Friday. His advisers said the results reflected not just from
balancing the budget, but also initiatives like improved access to
education and training and the opening of foreign markets to trade.
``There are enormous economic and social benefits from our
nation's high-employment economy,'' said Janet Yellen, the
chairwoman of the White House's Council of Economic Advisers.
Some of the biggest employment gains came in the construction
industry, which added 92,000 jobs in January. The increase
reflected the strength of the housing industry, which has been helped not just by declining interest rates but also by unusually
warm weather.
Service industries also showed solid job gains, as did
manufacturers, two areas expected to be hardest hit when the
effects of the Asian crisis hit the American economy. The major
harm from Asia is likely to come from the plunge in the value of
many Asian currencies relative to the dollar, a situation that is expected to lead to a surge of inexpensive imports into the United
States, hurting American competitors. And the weakness of the Asian
economies is also likely to lead to decreased demand for American
exports.
``The economy has been running on the fumes of the strength from
before the Asia shock,'' McCulley said. ``Those fumes will exhaust
themselves, and the manufacturing sector is going to start getting
beat up in the spring.''
The figures showed the unemployment rate for adult men declined
to 3.8 percent last month from 4.1 percent in December, the lowest
figure for almost two decades. The rate for adult women rose 0.4
percent, to 4.4 percent.
For the first time, the Labor Department broke out unemployment
by education level as well as gender, age and race. The analysis
showed unemployment rates dropped steadily with higher levels of
education. Among people with less than a high school education, the
rate in January was 7.2 percent.
Among high school graduates, the rate was 3.9 percent, and
college graduates, 1.9 percent.
</TEXT>
</BODY>
<TRAILER>
NYT-02-06-98 2219EST
</TRAILER>





































































































































































































































</TimeML>
