
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> SJMN91-06338157 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06338157 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Sununu; (Photo ran in PM editions only)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; GOVERNMENT; OFFICIAL; RESIGN; CONTROVERSY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  One of President Bush's sons has informed White House Chief of Staff John
Sununu that he has lost much of his support among Republicans, prompting an
intense effort by Sununu to hold on to his job by demonstrating his GOP
backing, White House and Republican sources said Monday.;   Sununu was told
Wednesday by Bush's son, George, that he had alienated members of the Cabinet,
the White House staff and the Republican political community, creating a
situation that puts his effectiveness in significant doubt, the sources said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SUNUNU BATTLES TO KEEP HIS JOB  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The message to the chief of staff was meant to be taken as a suggestion
that Sununu offer to resign, one highly placed source said. Instead, Sununu
sought to prove to the president that his supporters outnumber his critics and
that he should remain in his post.;   One senior official Monday described the
White House as "a collection of small groups of aides holding their breaths,"
waiting to see whether Sununu survives. One GOP source, reporting on a call
from the chief of staff to a Republican leader, said Sununu lamented that "the
noose is tightening around my neck, and I need your help.";   Another highly
placed source said the president's son met with Sununu last week after holding
a series of conversations about the structure of the White House staff and of
the campaign with other Bush loyalists and GOP activists. The source said the
younger Bush "sketched out for Sununu" problems the president is encountering
because of the chief of staff's tenure.;   "He was told . . . the handwriting
was on the wall," the source said Monday.;   That, the source said, was when
Sununu started calling congressional Republicans and asking them to tell Bush
that the conservative wing of the party, in particular, would  object if he
were fired.;   Officials said the president himself met with Sununu Sunday. A
source said the outcome of that session was unclear.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ANN DEVROY, Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911203  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
  4A  
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
  326  
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, December 3, 1991
00338157,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
































































































































</TimeML>
