
<TimeML
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../dtd/timeml_1.2.1.xsd">

<DOCNO> WSJ891030-0036 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891030 </DD>
<AN> 891030-0036. </AN>
<HL> Investor Group Makes
@  Bid for Dataproducts;
@  Liquidation Is Sought </HL>
<DD> 10/30/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> DPC </CO>
<IN> TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> WOODLAND HILLS, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A unit of DPC Acquisition Partners launched a $10-a-share tender offer for the shares outstanding of Dataproducts Corp., and said it would seek to liquidate the computer-printer maker "as soon as possible," even if a merger is n't consummated. 

   DPC Acquisition is controlled by Crescott Investment Associates, Wilson Investment Group, Kernel Corp. and Catalyst Partners. 
The investor group owns 1,534,600 Dataproducts common shares, or a 7.6% stake. 

   The offer is based on several conditions, including obtaining financing. 
DPC Acquisition said it had received the reasonable assurance of Chase Manhattan Bank N.A. that the financing can be obtained. 

   In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, DPC Acquisition said it expects it will need about $215 million to buy the shares and pay related fees and expenses. 
DPC Acquisition added that it has not begun discussions with financing sources, and said it expected to repay the amounts borrowed through proceeds of the liquidation. 

   Dataproducts officials declined to comment, and said they had not yet seen a suit filed in federal court by DPC Acquisition that seeks to nullify a standstill agreement between DPC Acquisition and Dataproducts. 

   Earlier this year, DPC Acquisition made a $15-a-share offer for Dataproducts, which the Dataproducts board said it rejected because the $283.7 million offer was not fully financed. 
Dataproducts has since started a restructuring, and has said it is not  for sale. 

</TEXT>



















































































































</TimeML>
